Our well-being is the foundation of our energy.
This energy fuels us across all dimensions —
work, learning, performance, awareness,
and the choices we make.
When you're in a place of optimal well-being,
things tend to flow smoothly and feel balanced.
You're more prepared to take on
whatever comes your way,
whether it's learning a new skill,
performing a difficult task,
reserving judgment in a difficult conversation,
or quickly executing a deliverable with a tight timeline.
But when your well-being is depleted,
it becomes harder to accomplish any of those things,
and harder to handle difficulties well.
For example, a stressful situation may quickly fill your mind
with anxious or even irrational thoughts.
Your heart may start to pound,
and your jaw may clench.
The inertia of your default tendency takes over,
and there's much less performing, learning and feeling positive.
Stress is not a bad thing in and of itself.
It's the accumulation of it at the extreme
that makes it hard for us to be and do our best.
Surprisingly, too little stress can also
have a negative impact on your well-being.
If you're feeling bored or disengaged,
it's hard to find the energy to power yourself through to a desired outcome.
When it comes to your well-being,
the optimal place to be is at the top of the U.
With no stimulation or stress at all,
you could end up feeling bored and fail to expand your capacity for growth.
On the other hand, when you're overwhelmed
or overly stressed for an extended period of time,
you could find yourself in the burnout zone.
This can also create a vicious cycle if you shift into survival mode,
which can perpetuate burnout and make it harder to recover.
In the cases of both boredom and burnout,
we tend to be less productive, avoid challenges,
and miss opportunities to learn and change.
At the top of the U, we're experiencing the optimal amount of stress
to maximize our performance and well-being.
Our awareness is at its peak,
we're more in control of our responses,
and we're primed to make better, positive choices.
Staying at the top of the U requires active attention.
When we manage our well-being,
we're better able to manage our stress.
And by actively managing our stress levels,
we improve our well-being.
Though stressful things can't be avoided,
we can change how we handle and cope with them
in ways that help us recover our well-being
and enhance our awareness and learning.
By doing these things we're able to help ourselves
in both the short and long term.
Don't worry if you can't always be at the top of the U.
Inevitably, there will be times
when you slide into boredom or burnout.
It's part of life.
Continually building your awareness of where you are
is part of what will improve your ability to adjust as needed.